In Python, there are ways to handle
在 Python 中 我们可以通过一些方式处理异常
exceptions so they don't always crush our program when they occur.
以避免异常始终使程序崩溃
Let's look back at this example that takes an input from the user.
我们回顾下这个示例 该示例会接受用户输入
We saw that when we ran this code,
我们发现 当我们运行这段代码时
it got an error when the user input something that can't be converted to an int.
如果用户输入无法转换为整型 就会出错
We can actually handle this error using a try statement.
我们实际上可以使用 try 语句处理这种错误
In a try statement,
在 try 语句中
the code inside the try block is first run
try 块中的代码会首先运行
and if Python runs into any exceptions while it's running this block,
如果 Python 在运行这段代码时遇到任何异常
it will jump to the code in the except block.
它将跳到 except 块中的代码
Here if I run this code and enter the word ten,
如果我运行这段代码并输入单词 ten 00:00:36,460 --&gt; 00:00:41,475 它会输出“That's not a valid number!”并继续转到代码的剩余部分
The program continues to run whether or not
无论程序是否在这个 try 块中遇到异常
it runs into an exception during this try block.
都会继续运行
For example, if I have a line after this try statement that prints attempted input,
例如 如果我在这个 try 语句之后添加一行代码 这行代码会输出尝试输入的值
you'll see this is printed in both cases.
你将发现在两种情况下都输出了这个结果
If we want this code to keep running until the user inputs a valid number,
如果我们希望代码继续运行 直到用户输入有效数字
we can use a while loop and break the loop if
我们可以使用 while 循环
all the code in the try block successfully executes.
并且当 try 块中的所有代码成功执行后退出循环
Here, the program keeps taking in input until I enter a valid number.
在此示例中 程序不断接受输入 直到我输入有效数字
If I enter a valid number,
如果我输入有效数字
this statement in the try block doesn't raise an exception.
try 块中的这个语句不会抛出异常
So it moves on to the next line where it breaks from the loop.
因此它移到下一行并退出循环
However, since it breaks the loop,
但是 因为它退出了循环
it never prints attempted input.
因此从未输出尝试输入的值
If we want this last line to always run after the try statement no matter what,
如果我们希望无论是什么情况 都运行 try 语句之后的最后一行代码
there is an optional component of the statement we can use.
可以使用该语句的一个可选组件 即 finally 块
Finally, now, attempted input will be printed when
现在 当程序在任何条件下退出这个 try 语句
the program is exiting this try statement under any conditions,
将会输出 Attempted Input
whether there is a break statement,
无论是有 break 语句 return 语句
return statement or error that causes this program to crash within except block.
还是出现导致程序在 except 块中崩溃的错误
You can read more about this in the notes below.
你可以在下面的注释中了解详情
The finally block is useful for cleaning up actions in your code.
finally 块适合清理代码中的操作
Later in the lesson, we will use this to close
在这节课的稍后阶段 当我们尝试在 try 语句中打开一个文件时
a file after attempting to open one in a try statement.
我们将使用 finally 块关闭该文件